<page>
<title>yestermorrow</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>5100114</id>
<revision>
<id>67393558</id>
<parentid>67393555</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-06-16T10:43:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J3133</username>
<id>3466327</id>
</contributor>
<comment>Undo revision 67393555 by [[Special:Contributions/J3133|J3133]] ([[User talk:J3133|talk]]) See “[[yester-morrow]]”</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="3037" xml:space="preserve">{{also|yester-morrow}}
==English==
===Etymology===
{{blend|en|yesterday|tomorrow}}
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# A day in the sequence of days from [[past]] to [[future]], emphasizing the connection between past and future events.
#* {{quote-journal|en|work=Curator: The Museum Journal |title=The museum as a communication system |year=1963 |month=October |volume=6|issue=4 |author=Harley W. Parker|passage=If we fail to take into consideration the works of these interpreters of “'''yestermorrow''',” we will be failing to monitor the pulse of contemporary thought and feeling.}}
#* {{quote-journal|en|work=Academy of Management Proceedings |title=Management History: Goals and Rationale |year=1973 |month=August |author=RJ Whiting |passage=This sets up an important guide in studying management history and one which could serve as a real beacon—&quot;'''yestermorrow'''&quot; —the idea of yesterday, today and tomorrow, a continuum of behavior.}}
#* {{quote-journal|en|work=Journal of Business Strategy |title=The evolution to market-driven quality |year=1992|volume=13|number=5 |author=RJ Bruno|passage=People are the ultimate core resource required to bridge from past success to future success — or &quot;'''yestermorrow'''.&quot;}}
#* {{quote-book|en|title=Once Upon an Island |author=Doug Cariou |year=2014 |ISBN=1490846433 |passage=I'll just put it back when I get home,” he thought, not at all suspecting it might be many long '''yestermorrows''' again before that might be so. }}
# A time outside of time; A time that cannot be fit into the normal timeline, possibly due to relativistic effects.
#* {{quote-book|en|title= Reflections from the Man Who Landed on the Moon in 1929 |author=Ray Bradbury |year=1970 |passage=Conceived in that journey, I was born in space. A child so birthed in desolations, homeless between '''yestermorrow''' and noon's midnight must have a proper name. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|title=From Spirit to Matter: New and Selected Poems, 1969-1996 |author=Carol Lee Sanchez |year=1997 |page=106 |passage=sombre lustre augers '''yestermorrows''' nowwhens in some other tense - future present past perfect }}
#* {{quote-book|en|title=Electronic Sue |author=Oliver Neale |year=2013 |page=241 |ISBN=1291538356 |passage=Susan Platz had always had the most distinctive voice - smoky and raspy one minute like her role in ''Who's That Bitch''?, and then sometimes it would sound tender, like in ''The Zone of Eternal '''Yestermorrows''''', then it might sound old, then young, like in ''The Space-time Straddler''. }}
===Adverb===
{{en-adv|-}}
# {{lb|en|obsolete}} In the recent past; [[the other day]].
#* {{quote-book|en|title=For the Master's Sake: A Story of the Days of Queen Mary |author=ES Holt |year=1877 |passage= “Father,” she faltered, in a low, shyvoice, “I heard you preach here '''yestermorrow'''.” }}
#* {{quote-book|en|title=The lord mayor |author=Emily Sarah Holt |year=1885 |page=332 |passage=Didst not see, she sent up sober sauce with the urchin '''yestermorrow''' ? &quot; }}
[[Category:en:Past]]</text>
<sha1>tawp3sced7y7kmu3nmb5iinbdkiajox</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
