<page>
<title>Ximenean</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>3051665</id>
<revision>
<id>67177611</id>
<parentid>65230584</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-05-28T17:04:34Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Equinox</username>
<id>84390</id>
</contributor>
<minor />
<comment>antonym is for adj, not noun</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="3677" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Etymology===
{{m|en|Ximénez}} or {{suffix|en|Ximenes|an}}
===Pronunciation===
* {{IPA|en|/hɪˈmeɪ.ni.ən/}}
===Adjective===
{{en-adj}}
# Of or pertaining to the [[cryptic crossword]] style used and defined by &quot;Ximenes&quot; ({{w|Derrick Somerset Macnutt}}), whereby an acceptable cryptic clue must have a precise [[definition]], a fair and strictly grammatical [[subsidiary]] indication, and no [[redundant]] elements beyond these.
#* {{quote-newsgroup|en|date=1992-07-28|author=Warren Usui|title=ACC 5 -- The rest of the clues.|url=https://groups.google.com/d/msg/rec.puzzles.crosswords/mjR6Xw2xWYo/PTsJu3aiBVYJ|group=rec.puzzles.crosswords|passage=For example, I did not follow a '''Ximenean''' rule that a member of a larger class cannot be used to define the class itself (one poster brought this up).}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2009|author=Dean Olsher|title=From Square One: A Meditation, with Digressions, on Crosswords|passage=Don Manley calls these non-'''Ximenean''' clues “wild and woolly” and worries they're far too common.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2012|author=David Astle|title=Puzzled: Secrets and clues from a life in words|passage={{...}} the '''Ximenean''' camp {{...}} makes up the hardliners, setters and solvers who insist on every clue being thoroughly sound in both grammar and execution {{...}}}}
# Pertaining to the religious teachings and publications of [[w:Francisco Jiménez de Cisneros|Ximénez de Cisneros]].
#* {{quote-text|en|year=1851|author=Paul MACLACHLAN|title=The Bible: Its Use and Abuse; Or, an Inquiry Into the Results of the Respective Doctrines of the Catholic and Protestant Churches, Relative to the Interpretation of the Word of God|page=186|passage=Speaking of the '''Ximenean''' Polyglot, Prescott calls it a “noble monument of piety, learning, and munificence, which entitles its author to the gratitude of the whole Christian world.”—Ferd. 5r Isab., Vol. III., p. 289.}}
#* '''1909''', ''The Journal of Theological Studies''
#*: In the oldest Mozarabic service-book (the Orationale Gothicum) the series of services of instruction for the Compétents (Missae Cate- chumenorum) is confined to three weeks, and not, as in the '''Ximenean''' printed service-books, extended to six weeks.
#* '''1911''', Arthur Cayley Headlam (Bishop of Gloucester), ''The Church Quarterly Review''
#*: The ''Orationale'' is a MS. of the highest antiquity, bearing throughout a character consistent with an older date than the MSS. which underlie the '''Ximenean''' Missal and Breviary
====Antonyms====
* {{l|en|Araucarian}}
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# A [[cruciverbalist]] or crossword fan who shares Ximenes's beliefs about fair crossword setting.
#* '''1977''', 'Apex', &quot;Stephen Sondheim 'The Lyric Poet of Broadway' ... and Crossword Composer?&quot;, ''Games &amp; Puzzles'', page xlix:
#*: I managed to complete a puzzle and as Ximenes enjoyed solving it, and as I thought he might welcome the opportunity to enter a clue writing contest himself, I decided to send the puzzle to a few more '''Ximeneans''' and set the name of the author of the quotation as the word to be clued.
#* {{cite-book|year=2012|passage=The home was in Leatherhead, which '''Ximeneans''' would despise as a signal for L, but let's keep with the action.|title=Puzzled: Secrets and clues from a life in words|author=David Astle|isbn=1847658164}}
#* {{cite-book|year=2013|passage=As Bunthorne puts it, 'Of course, I am a '''Ximenean'''. But I know that if it weren't for [Araucaria] pushing the boundaries, the rest of us wouldn't get anywhere at all.'|title=Pretty Girl In Crimson Rose|author=Sandy Balfour|isbn=1782394796}}
[[Category:English eponyms]]</text>
<sha1>mz9hjarwzlcd4xg77q31eq2ikgsb61n</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
