<page>
<title>Xemu</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>3439983</id>
<revision>
<id>63723044</id>
<parentid>54360269</parentid>
<timestamp>2021-08-22T17:35:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Geographyinitiative</username>
<id>285772</id>
</contributor>
<comment>/* English */ ===Etymology=== {{rfe|en}}</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="2986" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Etymology===
{{rfe|en}}
===Proper noun===
{{en-proper noun}}
# {{lb|en|Scientology}} {{alternative spelling of|en|Xenu}}
#* {{quote-journal|en|date=1985-11-17|author=Miami Herald staff|title=Scientology battered but not bowed in row over secret papers|newspaper=[[w:Miami Herald|Miami Herald]]|url=|page=12A|passage=Publication of secret documents blaming the world's troubles on an interplanetary tyrant named '''Xemu''' has held the Church of Scientology up to public ridicule. But church officials insist the disclosure will leave no long-term scars, and they predict the controversial organization will continue to gain members and to prosper.}}
#* {{quote-journal|en|date=1988-12-23|first=Stephen|last=Koff|title=Xemu's Cruel Response To Overpopulated World|newspaper=[[w:St. Petersburg Times|St. Petersburg Times]]|url=|page=10A|passage='''Xemu''' ruled the 90-planet Galactic Confederation 75-million years ago, when overpopulation was a problem. So '''Xemu''' solved the problem: He trapped selected beings and flew them to volcanoes on Earth, then called Teegeeach. He then dropped powerful H-bombs on the volcanoes. The beings were destroyed in a wall of fire. However, their spirits, or &quot;thetans,&quot; weren't. Gathering them into clusters, '''Xemu''' trapped the thetans in frozen alcohol and glycol.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1998|author=Robert Cogan|title=Critical Thinking: Step By Step|publisher=University Press of America|url=|isbn=|page=226|passage=After the explosions, the Thetan spirits, deprived of bodies, were packaged by '''Xemu''' and electronically implanted so they would reproduce in later generations of human beings. Each human today is a cluster of Thetans with one dominant. This is the cause of aberration, internal conflict and unhappiness. Only through paying for the costly further Scientology training could humans break through the wall of fire, revisit the '''Xemu''' incident, have their less dominant Thetans removed and at last become unaberrated, mentally healthy.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2011|author=Hugh B. Urban|title=[[w:The Church of Scientology: A History of a New Religion|The Church of Scientology: A History of a New Religion]]|publisher=Princeton University Press|url=|isbn=|page=103|passage=A more elaborate version of the Xenu/'''Xemu''' story appears in a lecture attributed to Hubbard from September 1968, also now widely available online. This provides further details of '''Xemu'''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; evil plot: apparently, the thetans were packed into refrigerated units, put onto DC 8 planes, and then blown up in volcanoes. After that, the disembodied thetans were collected, packed into boxes, and forced to watch 3-D movies. Meanwhile, a group of loyal officers revolted and captured '''Xemu''', locking him in the center of a mountain with an electric fence.}}
====Quotations====
* {{seemoreCites|en}}
====See also====
* {{l|en|Teegeeack}}
* {{l|en|Xenu}}
===Anagrams===
* {{anagrams|en|a=emux|Exum}}</text>
<sha1>i2fwaez1rmmucwod8bsjxswodzif9lp</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
