<page>
<title>Xenu</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>857156</id>
<revision>
<id>69488952</id>
<parentid>67887426</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-10-10T10:26:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Geographyinitiative</username>
<id>285772</id>
</contributor>
<minor />
<comment>/* Proper noun */ Archived</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="6323" xml:space="preserve">{{also|xenu}}
==English==
{{wikipedia}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{commonscat}}
{{wikisource|Memorandum Opinion on Religious Technology Center's And Arnaldo Lerma's Motions For Summary Judgment}}
===Alternative forms===
* {{l|en|Xemu}}
===Etymology===
{{rfe|en}}
===Proper noun===
{{en-proper noun}}
# {{lb|en|Scientology}} An [[extraterrestrial]] [[galactic]] leader said to have transported aliens to Earth 75 million years ago and murdered them with hydrogen bombs at sites of volcanoes, turning them into [[thetan]]s.
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=1960s
|last=Hubbard
|first=L. Ron
|authorlink=L. Ron Hubbard
|title={{w|OT III}}: Wall of Fire
|url=https://archive.org/details/armstrong.4.documents/1995-01-23%20Armstrong%20Declaration/page/n3/
|archiveurl2=https://archive.ph/RSZKU
|archivedate2=12 January 2013
|url2=http://www.xenu.net/archive/OTIII-scholar/
|text=He caused people to be brought to&lt;br&gt;Teegeeack (Earth) and put an H Bomb&lt;br&gt;on the principal volcanoes (Incident 2)&lt;br&gt;and then the Pacific area ones&lt;br&gt;were taken in boxes to Hawaii&lt;br&gt;and the Atlantic Area ones to&lt;br&gt;Las Palmas and there &quot;packaged.&quot;&lt;br&gt;His name was '''Xenu'''. He used&lt;br&gt;renegades.Various misleading&lt;br&gt;data by means of circuits etc.&lt;br&gt;were placed in the implants.}}
#* {{quote-journal
|en
|date=NOV. 23, 1985
|author=Robert Welkos, Joel Sappell
|title=Scientologists Win Major Court Victory Over Defectors, Documents
|journal={{w|Los Angeles Times}}
|issn=0458-3035
|oclc=3638237
|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200712052654/https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1985-11-23-me-1278-story.html
|archivedate=July 12, 2020
|text=The documents Scott took are a refinement of Hubbard’s account of '''Xemu''', assertedly an evil tyrant who planted the seeds of aberrant behavior in people 75 million years ago.&lt;br&gt;According to documents obtained previously by The Times in Los Angeles Superior Court, Hubbard contends that '''Xemu''' trapped people in a compound of frozen alcohol and glycol and deposited them in 10 volcanoes. '''Xemu''' then dropped nuclear bombs on the volcanoes, according to Hubbard, destroying the people but freeing their spirits, which clustered together and were brainwashed by '''Xemu'''.
|brackets=on}}
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=1986
|author=Stewart Lamont
|title={{w|Religion Inc.|Religion Inc.: The Church of Scientology}}
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9UwwAAAAYAAJ
|location=[[London]]
|publisher={{w|Harrap}}
|ISBN=0-245-54334-1
|OCLC=23079677
|OL=2080316M
|page=50
|text=Seventy-five million years ago there was a galactic confederation consisting of seventy-six planets which had an over-population problem. The head of the confederation was named '''Xenu''' and he resolved that he would entice the entire population of the confederacy to Earth (called Teegeeach) and blow them up.[...]Contacting the BTs is done telepathically and they are then guided back down the time-track to the moment seventy-five million years ago when '''Xenu''' vaporized them, which is known as Incident 2.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2007|author=Una McGovern|title=Chambers Dictionary of the Unexplained|url=http://www.amazon.com/Chambers-Dictionary-Unexplained-Una-McGovern/dp/0550102159|isbn=0550102159|publisher=Chambers|page=607|passage=At the heart of Scientology’s belief system is the story of a galactic dictator called '''Xenu''' who, 76 million years ago, imprisoned the billions of people of the 75 planets of the Galactic Federation in volcanoes on Earth and dropped H-bombs on them. This traumatic event separated the thetans from their bodies. These deeply troubled thetans attach themselves in their millions to humans today; and are responsible for illness, perversion and many of the other problems of the human race. Advanced levels of auditing can help Scientologists to rid themselves of these ‘body thetans’.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2008|author=Michael Streeter|title=Behind Closed Doors: The Power and Influence of Secret Societies|publisher=New Holland Publishers|url=|isbn=|page=219|passage=That incident, the story of '''Xenu''', is an extremely important incident theologically, because it explains why everyone is infested with body thetans here on earth. It is a serious event considered to have happened.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2011|author=Janet Reitman|title=[[w:Inside Scientology: The Story of America's Most Secretive Religion|Inside Scientology: The Story of America's Most Secretive Religion]]|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|url=|isbn=|page=100|passage=More than a few Scientologists read the '''Xenu''' story as “a bizarre science fiction story,” as one former member described it. But fearing they'd be denounced for doubting Hubbard's teachings—to do so would be a thought crime — they held their tongue.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2011|author=Hugh B. Urban|title=[[w:The Church of Scientology: A History of a New Religion|The Church of Scientology: A History of a New Religion]]|publisher=Princeton University Press|url=|isbn=|page=103|passage=A more elaborate version of the '''Xenu'''/Xemu story appears in a lecture attributed to Hubbard from September 1968, also now widely available online.}}
====Quotations====
* {{seemoreCites|en}}
====See also====
* [[Teegeeack]]
===Further reading===
* {{cite-journal|authorlink=Leonie Brinkema|first=Leonie|last=Brinkema|title=[[s:Memorandum Opinion on Religious Technology Center's And Arnaldo Lerma's Motions For Summary Judgment|Memorandum Opinion on Religious Technology Center's And Arnaldo Lerma's Motions For Summary Judgment]]|url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Memorandum_Opinion_on_Religious_Technology_Center%27s_And_Arnaldo_Lerma%27s_Motions_For_Summary_Judgment|publisher=[[w:United States District Court for the Eastern District of Virginia|United States District Court for the Eastern District of Virginia]]|journal=Religious Technology Center v. Lerma|date=October 4, 1996}}
* {{cite-journal|last=Kent|first=Stephen A.|authorlink=Stephen A. Kent|url=http://www.solitarytrees.net/pubs/skent/creation.htm|journal=Religious Studies and Theology|volume=18|issue=2|date=December 1999|pages=97-126|title=The Creation of 'Religious' Scientology|accessdate=1 February 2012|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050208092739/http://solitarytrees.net/pubs/skent/creation.htm|archivedate=8 February 2005}}</text>
<sha1>22mozva4uusas4p25ch1f96iuq273ix</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
