<page>
<title>ycleped</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>1907840</id>
<revision>
<id>65825983</id>
<parentid>64614607</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-02-14T12:36:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Esme Shepherd</username>
<id>2461284</id>
</contributor>
<comment>/* Adjective */ quotation</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="3036" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Adjective===
{{head|en|adjective}}
# {{alternative spelling of|en|yclept}}
#* {{RQ:Butler Hudibras|part=2|canto=I|page=106|passage=There is a tall long-sided Dame, / (But wondrous light) '''ycleped''' ''Fame'', / That like a thin ''Camelion'' Bourds / He[r] self on Air, and eats her words: {{...}}}}
#* {{RQ:Irving History of New York|volume=II|chapter=Shewing How Profound Secrets are Strangely Brought to Light;{{nb...|with the Proceedings of Peter the Headstrong when He Heard of the Misfortune of General Von Poffenburgh}}|page=86|passage=Sometimes in consequence of some flagrant villany, he would abscond from the garrison, {{...}} squatting himself down on the edge of a pond catching fish for hours together, and bearing no little resemblance to that notable bird '''ycleped''' the Mud-poke.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=Dawson Turner|chapter=Letter X. Early Pointed Architecture—Cathedral—Episcopal Palace|title=Account of a Tour in Normandy;{{nb...|Undertaken Chiefly for the Purpose of Investigating the Architectural Antiquities of the Duchy, with Observations on Its History, on the Country, and on Its Inhabitants. Illustrated with Numerous Engravings.}}|location=London|publisher={{...|Printed [by]}} [C. Sloman] for John  and Arthur Arch,{{nb...|Cornhill.}}|year=1820|volume=I|section=footnote&amp;nbsp;†|page=163|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=1BpVAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA163|oclc=1003889894|passage=The event is described in the metrical history of Rouen, composed by a minstrel '''ycleped''' ''Poirier, the limper''.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1842|author={{w|Letitia Elizabeth Landon}}|title=Lady Anne Granard|volume=1|pages=252-253|text=We by no means mean to say that Lady Anne's happy and pleasant little party would not have received a new impetus if a Moore, a Bulwer, a Hook, or those monopolists of beauty and wit, Mrs. Gore and Mrs. Norton, or those daughters of Apollo, '''ycleped''' Mitford, Pardoe, and Strickland had been mingled with her &quot;blue spirits and grey;&quot; but we do mean to say that they were very happy without them, and that much, perhaps all, of the &quot;feast of reason and the flow of soul,&quot; for which these distinguished individuals are loved, and sought, and honoured, would have been lost in the melée of dancing, singing, chattering, and flirting, to which the major part of the visitants were devoted.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=Frances Anne Kemble|authorlink=Fanny Kemble|chapter=|title=Journal of a Residence on a Georgian Plantation in 1838–1839|location=London|publisher=[[w:Longman|Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts, &amp; Green]]|year=1863|page=176|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=SV5EAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA176|oclc=367550253|passage=The damsel, '''ycleped''' Louisa, made rather a shame-faced obeisance, and her old grandmother went on to inform me that she had only lately been forgiven by the overseer for an attempt to run away from the plantation.}}
----
==Middle English==
===Verb===
{{head|enm|verb form}}
# {{inflection of|enm|clepen||past participle}}</text>
<sha1>2kiherfeirz59ly829lbvnaz395amiu</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
