<page>
<title>yearthousand</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>4600514</id>
<revision>
<id>64004814</id>
<parentid>62922538</parentid>
<timestamp>2021-09-22T19:32:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>NadandoBot</username>
<id>394541</id>
</contributor>
<comment>Replacing non-breaking space</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="2529" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Alternative forms===
* {{alter|en|year-thousand|year thousand}}
===Etymology===
From {{com|en|year|thousand}}. Compare {{cog|nl|jaarduizend|t=millennium}}, {{cog|de|Jahrtausend|t=millennium}}, {{cog|no|årtusen|t=millennium}}, {{cog|is|árþúsund|t=millennium}}, {{cog|sv|årtusende|t=millennium}}.
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# {{lb|en|very|_|rare}} A [[millennium]] {{gl|a [[period]] of a [[thousand]] [[year]]s}}.
#* '''1859''', G. SEYFFARTH, A.M., PH. D., D.D., ''SUMMARY OF RECENT DISCOVERIES BIBLICAL CHRONOLOGY'':
#*: Because, according to the peculiar chronology of the oriental Jews, the sixth millenium{{sic}} or '''year-thousand''' after the creation expired in 1810.
#* '''1867''', The English Cyclopedia:
#*: {{quote|en|It is probable that a hundred years hence the students of European literature will have much better means at command than ourselves, to take a comprehensive view of the literature of Europe during the earlier part of this “'''Yearthousand''',&quot;—to use a Germanism which is in many respects preferable to “Millennium.&quot;}}
#* '''1880''', John Lothrop Motley, ''History of the United Netherlands'':
#*: Human history, so far as it has been written, is at best a mere fragment; for the few centuries or '''year-thousands''' of which there is definite record are as nothing compared to the millions of unnumbered years during which man has perhaps walked the earth.
#* '''1902''', Journal of the American Oriental Society:
#*: {{...}} “the War (of the gods and their elder brothers, the devils) lasted thirty-two '''yearthousands''',” xii. 33. 26.
#* '''2000''', August Hermann Francke, ''Gśam-yul Na Bśad Paʼi Ge-sar Gyi Sgruṅ Bźugs So'':
#*: One branch of them went north-east into North China and settled there, or stayed on in their original home in the Hwang-Ho valley, long before 2000 B.C., and there it became the ancient Chinese people, who built up a very high and original type of civilisation before 1500 B.C., which independently of any other cultures reached its highest point during the first '''year-thousand''' before Christ, and attained still further development through contact with Buddhism and Indian civilisation during the first '''year-thousand''' after Christ.
#* '''2014''', Anne Kari B. Solstad, ''Off darkness...: A journey out of the landscape of depression'':
#*: This has been into the genes through out '''yearthousands'''. It has been accepted. Women have been for trade or exchange due to sex in all times.
#: {{meronyms|en|yearhundred}}</text>
<sha1>ii009ba1fc0thsxd36nf2tzyi9q0xuc</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
