<page>
<title>yearhundred</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>3620229</id>
<revision>
<id>62922539</id>
<parentid>62642311</parentid>
<timestamp>2021-06-19T19:44:52Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Equinox</username>
<id>84390</id>
</contributor>
<minor />
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="2276" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Etymology===
From {{com|en|year|hundred}}. Compare {{cog|sco|yeirhunder|t=century}}, {{cog|stq|Jierhunnert|t=century}}, {{cog|de|Jahrhundert|t=century}}, {{cog|da|책rhundrede|t=century}}, {{cog|sv|책rhundrade|t=century}}, {{cog|no|책rhundre|t=century}}.
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# {{lb|en|very|_|rare}} A [[period]] of a [[hundred]] consecutive [[year]]s; a [[century]].
#* '''1878''', Carl S채ve, ''Some runic stones in Northern Sweden'':
#*: My oldest specimen is Danish, an &quot;overgang&quot;-stone (bearing Old-Northern as well as Scandinavian runes) from about the first half of the 9th century. The runic examples thus run down from the 9th to the 14th '''yearhundred'''.
#* '''1883''', George Stephens, ''Prof. S. Bugge's studies on Northern mythology shortly examined'':
#*: It may have been copied from the Northern Baldor myth, for Gothic arms and arts had been known for many centuries in the East and West in the 6th '''yearhundred''', and Greek-writing heretics and bookmakers copied from all quarters.
&lt;!--#*'''1894''', George Stephens, ''The runes, whence came they'':
#*: Date about the 5th '''yearhundred''' A. D. Bears: IGING ON (= of) H/EU owns this grave. ... Date about the 7th '''yearhundred''' A. D. Seems to say: Aye shall they have lustre on the fresh floor of their tumulus, [...]--&gt;
#* '''1914''', Records of the American Catholic Historical Society of Philadelphia, Volume 25:
#*: Are we thereby to date also St. Peter and St. Paul, St. Stephen and St. James in the Third Century, the Fourth and still posthumous '''Yearhundreds''' of the Christian era?
#* '''1983''', Michael Cox, ''M.R. James, an informal portrait'':
#*: And this last, is it from out today's times forgettinghood or our much to be bewailed speechshapelearningness's unwisdomship, is to a nineteenth '''yearhundred''' period's togethergatheringreceivingsaloon sad un-befitted.
#* '''1996''', Eesti NSV Riiklik Etnograafiamuuseum, Eesti Rahva Muuseum, ''Eesti Rahva Muuseumi aastaraamat'':
#*: On the territory of Estonia three main educational ideologies can be differentiated during the '''yearhundred''' concerned: religious-lutheran, strict disciplinarianism and the one orientated to nationalism and education.
#: {{holonyms|en|yearthousand}}
[[Category:en:Hundred]]</text>
<sha1>ambllnmihzgjmm9791q2iedw4ompteu</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
