<page>
<title>yetling</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>6017788</id>
<revision>
<id>67946846</id>
<parentid>54370914</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-07-14T07:53:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Equinox</username>
<id>84390</id>
</contributor>
<minor />
<comment>====Alternative forms==== * {{alt|en|yetlin}}</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="3686" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Etymology===
From {{inh|en|enm|yetling}}, {{m|enm|yetlyng}}, {{m|enm|ȝetlynge}}, equivalent to {{suffix|en|yet|t1=to pour|ling}}.
===Noun===
{{en-noun|~}}
# {{label|en|UK|chiefly|Scotland|obsolete}} [[cast iron|Cast iron]].
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1794 |title=The Statistical Account of Scotland: Drawn Up from the Communications of the Ministers of the Different Parishes |author=John Sinclair |page=178 |passage=Scots ploughs, very neatly made, and covered with '''yetling''', are the only kind used in this parish. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1815 |title=The Gentleman Farmer: Being an Attempt to Improve Agriculture by Subjecting it to the Test of Rational Principles |author=Henry Home (Lord Kames) |page=54 |passage=Rollers are of different kinds, stone, '''yetling''', wood. Each of these has its advantages. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1884 |title=The History of Old Dundee, Narrated Out of the Town Council Register |author= |page=212-213 |passage=Having afterwards resolved upon renewing the armament, they instructed the Dean of Guild &quot; to sell the auld pieces callit heidsticks being in the steeple to the gritest avail, and wair and bestow the money gotten therefor upon sufficient '''yetling''' ordinance to the common use of the burgh.&quot; }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1896 |title=The Water of Leith from Source to Sea |author=John Geddie |page=32 |passage=A caller burn runs wimpling clear, Out o'er its rocky bed ; Where sits the rural '''yetling''' chair, For youth and hoary head, To rest themselves beside the stream And hear its murmuring. }}
# {{label|en|UK|chiefly|Scotland|by extension}} A small [[cauldron]], or rounded [[pot]], typically, but not always, made of cast iron.
#: {{syn|en|yet}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1842 |title=Local Collections; Or, Records of Remarkable Events, Connected with the Borough of Gateshead |page=50 |ISBN= |passage=Still, it occurs to me that Yetlington is more probably indebted to its name from being the spot where &quot; '''yetlings'''&quot; were made. To this day the metal pot used by the muggers is known by that appellation in its immediate neighhourhood, and bears a striking resemblance to a sacred utensil used during the sacrifices of the Romans. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1859|author=Jane Anne Winscom|title=Onward: or, The mountain Clamberers : a Tale of Progress |page=43 |passage=Mother had lifted the '''yetling''' off the fire, and left it there,&quot; pointing to the middle of the room ; &quot; and she comes running along and tumbles in. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1880 |title=A Descriptive Catalogue of Antiquities, Chiefly British, at Alnwick Castle |author=John Collingwood Bruce |passage=A bronze '''yetling''', or tripod caldron, with an angular handle at each side. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1987 |title=Traditional Food in Yorkshire |author=Peter C. D. Brears |page=79 |passage=Baking in the turf-burning areas of the North Yorkshire Moors was also undertaken in a '''yetling''', a cylindrical cast-iron vessel perhaps a foot in diameter and five inches in height which hung over the fire from a reckon-hook. }}
# {{label|en|UK|chiefly|Scotland}} A small cast iron [[ball]].
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1896 |title=The County Histories of Scotland - Volume 4 |page=231|passage=A more recent conjecture traces a connection between it and the game still, or not long ago, played at New Year with '''yetlings''' or balls of cast iron on the sands near the Skilleys of Wemyss, in which, as in the North German Klotschiessen, the player who drives the ball to the goal in the fewest number of strokes wins. }}
====Alternative forms====
* {{alt|en|yetlin}}
===Anagrams===
* {{anagrams|en|a=egilnty|Tingley|yelting}}</text>
<sha1>9z1jorvnecp5tn6ijnf27s1lgtfe2j4</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
