<page>
<title>Yangchow</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>7103702</id>
<revision>
<id>67960286</id>
<parentid>63601549</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-07-15T16:17:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dunderdool</username>
<id>3953866</id>
</contributor>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="3153" xml:space="preserve">==English==
===Etymology===
The {{w|postal romanization}} of the {{bor|en|cmn|-}} Chinese pronunciation for {{zh-l|揚州}}.
===Pronunciation===
* {{enPR|yǎngʹchouʹ|yängʹjōʹ}}
===Proper noun===
{{en-proper noun}}
# {{alternative form of|en|Yangzhou}}
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=1915
|author={{w|Marshall Broomhall}}
|title=The Jubilee Story of the China Inland Mission
|url=https://archive.org/details/jubileechinamis00broouoft/
|OCLC=1113769946
|page=63
|pageurl=https://archive.org/details/jubileechinamis00broouoft/page/63/
|passage=With the opening of '''Yangchow''' the Mission had struck out in a new direction, for that city was situated on the northern section of the Grand Canal, which in those days, before the sea-route had become popular, was the highroad from the south to Peking and the northern provinces.}}
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=1927
|author=William James Hail
|title=Tsêng Kuo Fan And The Taiping Rebellion: With a Short Sketch of His Later Career
|url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.284652/
|publisher=Yale History Press
|OCLC=1027538276
|page=188
|pageurl=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.284652/page/n101/
|text=The resourcefulness of the Taipings was not too greatly occupied with the establishment of the Celestial Capital to prevent reaching out for the vital strategic centers of Chinkiang and '''Yangchow''', the former a commanding site at the intersection of the Grand Canal with the Yangtse River, the latter on the canal about twenty-five or thirty miles away, both together controlling that vital artery through which flowed the supplies of tribute grain to the capital.}}
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=1970
|author=S. A. M. Adshead
|title=The Modernization of the Chinese Salt Administration, 1900-1920
|url=https://archive.org/details/modernizationofc0000adsh/
|location=[[Cambridge]], [[Massachusetts]]
|publisher={{w|Harvard University Press}}
|ISBN=0-674-58060-5
|LCCN=77-120315
|OCLC=805621059
|page=19
|pageurl=https://archive.org/details/modernizationofc0000adsh/page/19/
|text=Every aspect of the salt trade required official sanction and the issue of permits. As an illustration, let us consider the marketing of a consignment of salt from the Huai-nan salines to an up-river port such as Hankow or Ta-t'ung. The yard merchant (''ch'ang-shang'') at the salines had to report his output of salt daily to the salt receiver (''ch'ang-kuan''), and could carry salt for sale to Shih-erh-wei only on the requisition of the Huai-nan general office (Huai-nan tsung-chü) at '''Yangchow''', transmitted through the salt receiver; when he received this, the had to apply back to '''Yangchow''' for a transport permit (''ch'ung-yen chih-chao'') and to his local branch office (''fen-ssu'') for a cargo certificate (''ts'ang-tan'').}}
#* {{quote-book
|en
|year=December 2010
|ISBN=978-1-59328-277-6
|title=A Foreign Devil in China
|author=John Pollock
|publisher=World Wide Publications
|page=33}}
#*:In a riot half a century earlier, Hudson Taylor had nearly lost his life at '''Yangchow''', once the city of Marco Polo.
===Further reading===
* {{R:OneLook}}
* {{R:TheFreeDictionary}}</text>
<sha1>8ktlam8zozx4yk2egiadufstkzk736r</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
