<page>
<title>Xanadu</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>58895</id>
<revision>
<id>65334335</id>
<parentid>65334332</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-01-13T22:46:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jberkel</username>
<id>1580588</id>
</contributor>
<comment>/* English */</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="4684" xml:space="preserve">==English==
{{wikipedia}}
===Alternative forms===
* {{alter|en|Shangdu}}
===Etymology===
From {{bor|en|cmn|上都|tr=Shàngdū}}. The first Romanized form comes from [[w:Marco Polo|Marco Polo]]'s writings in Italian as ''Shan-Du''. In 1617, ''Purchas his Pilgrimage{{...|, or Relations of the World and the Religions observed in all Ages and Places discovered, from the Creation unto this Present...}}'' by {{w|Samuel Purchas}} was published in London, containing the phrase “In Xamdu did Cublai Can build a stately Palace” on page&amp;nbsp;472. This was the inspiration for Coleridge's poem which uses the spelling ''Xanadu''.
===Pronunciation===
* {{IPA|en|/ˈzænəduː/}}
* {{audio|en|LL-Q1860 (eng)-Vealhurl-Xanadu.wav|Audio (UK)}}
===Proper noun===
{{en-proper noun}}
# {{lb|en|historical}} The summer capital of [[w:Kublai Khan|Kublai Khan]]'s empire.
#* {{RQ:Coleridge Christabel|page=55|passage=In '''Xanadu''' did {{smallcaps|Kubla Khan}} / A stately pleasure-dome decree: / Where {{smallcaps|Alph}}, the sacred river, ran / Through caverns measureless to man / Down to a sunless sea.}}
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# {{lb|en|figurative}} A place full of beauty, happiness and wonder.
#: {{syn|en|heaven|paradise|Shangri-La}}
#* {{quote-journal
|year=1991
|volume=261-262
|journal=Uncle Scrooge
|title=[[w:Tralla La|Return to Xanadu]]
|page=5
|author=Don Rosa
|1=en
|footer=Refers to [[w:Kubla Khan|Kubla Khan]], a poem by [[w:Samuel Taylor Coleridge|Samuel Taylor Coleridge]].
|text=That's from the poem of the legend of Kubla Kahn's palace in the lost valley of Xanadu! Alph was the river in the legend! Unca Scrooge, ''this'' is the road to '''Xanadu'''! You've hit the jackpot! The most wondrous valley on earth! The land of milk and honey!}}
#* {{quote-song
|title=Xanadu
|author=[[w:Party Animals (music group)|Party Animals]]
|year=2003
|1=en
|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Alk5TQZoUPw
|text=A place where nobody dared to go&lt;br&gt;The love that we came to know&lt;br&gt;They call it '''Xanadu'''&lt;br&gt;And now, open your eyes and see&lt;br&gt;What we have made is real&lt;br&gt;We are in '''Xanadu'''}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2013| title=In Translation: Translators on Their Work and What It Means |author=Esther Allen, Susan Bernofsky | page=240| passage=The lyric, as the ideological critics in particular would have it, plays host to a panoply of enticing pipe dreams conjured up by benighted idealists whose visions are doomed in advance to frustration as reality fails, time and again, to ratify their various '''Xanadus''' and Byzantiums.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2013| title=The Alpine Xanadu|author=Mary Daheim | page=319| passage=I never guessed that when I stumbled into the sheriff's office on a warm August afternoon, I'd met my future. I'd had no dream of finding my own little Eden, my snowcapped paradise, my '''Xanadu''' in the Valley of the Sky. }}
# An [[opulent]] [[building]] or [[resort]] that provides [[entertainment]] or [[luxurious]] [[living]].
#: {{syn|en|pleasure palace}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=1994| title=Hollywood Censored: Morality Codes, Catholics, and the Movies|author=Gregory D. Black | page=21| passage=“The United States in the twenties was dotted with a thousand '''Xanadus''',” wrote movie-theater historian Ben Hall.&quot;}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2003| title=Marketing Apocalypse: Eschatology, Escapology and the Illusion of the End.|author=Jim Bell, Stephen Brown, David Carson | page=| passage=The postmodern '''Xanadus''' that support this hallucination in the desert offer a particularly attractive paradise of the popular.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2011| title=Oranges|author=John McPhee | page=68| passage=The Normans went Muslim with such remarkable style that even Muslim poets were soon praising the new Norman '''Xanadus'''. Of one such place, which included nine brooks and a small lake with an island covered with lemon and orange trees, the poet Abd ur-Rahman Ibn Mohammed Ibn Omar wrote: {{...}}}}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2012| title=Fools Die |author=Mario Puzo | page=6| passage=Under the blazing Nevada sun, a dozen '''Xanadus''' glittered with million-watt neon signs. }}
#* {{quote-book|en|year=2012| title=Times &amp; Tides: A Middle Harbour Memoir|author=Gavin Souter | page=| passage=My only company among the vanished pleasures was a four-foot-long goanna, warily immobile on the stone wall, then slowly climbing a tree trunk, pausing now and then to check on me. Elsewhere in Middle Harbour there are half a dozen other abandoned '''Xanadus'''.}}
===See also===
* {{l|en|Kaiping}}
===References===
* {{R:OneLook}}
* {{R:Century 1911}}
[[Category:en:Cities in China]]
[[Category:English terms derived from toponyms]]</text>
<sha1>pbhnbjzjvla5v0e3o7r210tb2t6h27a</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
