<page>
<title>xebec</title>
<ns>0</ns>
<id>70325</id>
<revision>
<id>69533561</id>
<parentid>68857674</parentid>
<timestamp>2022-10-17T01:42:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ExcarnateSojourner</username>
<id>3854170</id>
</contributor>
<minor />
<comment>/* Pronunciation */ +en rhyme (using [[MediaWiki:Gadget-AjaxEdit.js|AjaxEdit]])</comment>
<model>wikitext</model>
<format>text/x-wiki</format>
<text bytes="9903" xml:space="preserve">==English==
{{was wotd|2018|September|27}}
===Etymology===
[[File:Christian Boers Pirataatak 1769 cr No 3.jpg|thumb|A 1769 drawing of a xebec used by [[Algeria]]n [[pirate#Noun|pirates]] by [[w:no:Christian Børs (sjømann)|Christian Børs]], a [[sailor]] from [[Bergen]], [[Norway]], who was taken prisoner in Algeria]]
From {{der|en|fr|chebec}}, from {{der|en|es|jabeque|xabeque}} or {{der|en|ca|xabec}} or {{der|en|it|sciabecco}}, from {{der|en|ar|شُبَّاك|t=fishing-net}}. Not to confuse with the {{m|en|sambuq}}, an [[Indian Ocean|Indian-Sea]] vessel.
{{root|en|ar|ش ب ك}}
===Pronunciation===
* {{a|RP}} {{IPA|en|/ˈziːbɛk/}}
** {{audio|en|LL-Q1860 (eng)-Vealhurl-xebec.wav|Audio (UK)}}
* {{a|GA}} {{IPA|en|/ˈzibɛk/}}
* {{rhymes|en|iːbɛk|s=2}}
* {{hyphenation|en|xe|bec}}
===Noun===
{{en-noun}}
# A small two-[[mast#Noun|masted]], and later three-masted, [[Mediterranean]] [[transport]] [[ship#Noun|ship]] with an [[overhanging#Adjective|overhanging]] [[bow#Noun|bow]] and [[stern#Noun|stern]]. {{defdate|from mid 18th c.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=“a sea-officer” &amp;#91;{{w|Thomas Mathews}}?&amp;#93;|title=A Narrative of the Proceedings of His Majesty’s Fleet in the Mediterranean, and the Combined Fleets of France and Spain, from the Year 1741, to March 1744.{{nb...|Including an Accurate Account of the Late Fight near Toulon, and the Causes of Our Miscarriage: The Lines of Battle on Both Sides, Plans of Villa Franca, Naples, Hieres Bay, and Toulon: The French Admiral’s Journal in French and English, from the Time He Left Toulon, until He Anchored with His Fleet in Alicant Road. Likewise Some Signals Greatly Wanted on the Late Occasion: And a List of Captains and Lieutenants Made by Admiral Mathews in the Mediterranean, Their Different Removes, &amp;c. With Many Useful Observations}}|location=London|publisher=Printed for J. Millan,{{nb...|near Whitehall}}|year=1744|page=25|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=KuVbAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA25|oclc=883653443|passage=Fourteen '''''Xebecks''''' loaded with Ammunition, Cannon, and other warlike Stores from ''Majorca'', bound to any Part of ''Italy'', where they could be landed for the Uſe of the ''Spaniſh'' Army, having got ſafe to ''Genoa'' in the latter End of ''June'', Admiral ''Mathews'' on board of the ''Namur'', with the ''Barfleur'', ''Norfolk'', ''Princeſs Caroline'', ''Ipſwich'' and ''Revenge'' went there, and concluded a Treaty; {{...}}}}
#* {{quote-journal|en|title=Ships Taken by the French and Spaniards, August 1746|editor=Sylvanus Urban [pseudonym; {{w|Edward Cave}}]|magazine=[[w:The Gentleman's Magazine|The Gentleman’s Magazine]]|location=London|publisher-Printed by E[dward] Cave, jun.{{nb...|at St John's Gate}}|month=September|year=1746|volume=XVI|page=459|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=cU1GAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA459|oclc=192374019|passage=An Engliſh privateer, Capt. Clymer, taken by two Spaniſh '''xebecs''' in the Weſt Indies.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=S[amuel] Ancell|authorlink=Samuel Ancell|chapter=V|title=A Circumstantial Journal of the Long and Tedious Blockade and Siege of Gibraltar, from the 12th of September, 1779, (the Day the Garrison Opened Their Batteries against the Spaniards) to the 23d Day of February, 1783;{{nb...|Containing, an Authentic Account of the Most Remarkable Transactions, in which the Enemy’s Motions, Works, Approaches, Firings, &amp;c. are Particularly Described. In a Series of Letters, from the Author to His Brother}}|location=Liverpool|publisher=Printed by Charles Wosencroft|year=1784|page=27|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=kA0MAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA17|oclc=642356192|passage=This afternoon, Wind W.S.W. an Engliſh brig appeared in the offing; ſhe was chaſed by a '''xebec''' and ſeveral gallies, but fortunately got ſafe into New Mole: She brings the joyful and happy tidings of a fine fleet being within twenty-four hours ſail of the Garriſon.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=attributed to {{w|Mathew Carey}}|chapter=[Appendix.] No. IV. Extract of a Letter from {{smallcaps|John M‘Shane}}, Captain of the Minerva, to {{smallcaps|William Bell}}, dated Algiers, November 13, 1793|title=A Short History of Algiers, with a Concise View of the Origin of the Rupture between Algiers and the United States.{{nb...|To which is Added a Copious Appendix: Containing Letters from Captain Penrose, M‘Shane, and Sundry Other American Captives, with a Description of the Treatment Those Prisoners Experienced}}|edition=3rd improved|location=New York, N.Y.|publisher=Published by [[w:Evert Augustus Duyckinck|Evert Duyckinck]],{{nb...|110 Pearl-street}}; W[illiam] W. Vermilye, printer|date=13 November 1793|year_published=1805|page=82|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=CMgRAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA82|oclc=80923186|passage=On the 18th October, about five leagues from Gibraltar, we were boarded by a '''zebeck''' of 20 guns, belonging to this place, who after coming within musket-shot, kept up a constant firing with small arms, until they manned our yards from theirs, then the firing ceased, and they came down sword in hand, spared our lives, but nothing else, having stripped us of the clothes we had on, and put us on board the '''zebeck''', {{...}}}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=John Charnock|chapter=ST. VINCENT, Sir John Jervis, K.B. Earl of|title=Biographia Navalis; or, Impartial Memoirs of the Lives and Characters of Officers of the Navy of Great Britain, from the Year 1660 to the Present Time;{{nb...|Drawn from the Most Authentic Sources, and Disposed in a Chronological Arrangement}}|location=London|publisher=Printed for R. Faulder,{{nb...|Bond-Street}}|year=1798|volume=VI (Being the Second Volume of the Continuation)|section=footnote ‡|page=406|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=0EMOAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA406|oclc=858348049|passage=Soon after this time he &amp;#91;{{w|John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent}}&amp;#93; was put into the Experiment as acting captain, on account of a ſhort indiſpoſition which attacked [[w:Sir Richard Strachan, 6th Baronet|ſir Richard Strachan]], and ſignalized himſelf in the moſt remarkable manner during an action with a very large '''zebec''', carrying 26 heavy guns and 400 men.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=William James|authorlink=William James (naval historian)|chapter=Encounters of Detached Ships|title=The Naval History of Great Britain, from the Declaration of War by France, in February 1793; to the Accession of George IV. in January 1820; {{...|with an Account of the Origin and Progressive Increase of the British Navy; Illustrated, from the Commencement of the Year 1793, by a Series of Tabular Abstracts, Contained in a Separate Quarto Volume. [...]}} In Five Volumes|location=London|publisher=Printed for Baldwin, Cradock, and Joy|year=1824|volume=IV|page=104|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=fV0PAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA104|oclc=606079942|passage=On the 13th of December, at eight in the morning, Cape St. Martin, coast of Spain, bearing south-south-west six leagues, the british 16-gun brig-sloop Halcyon, captain Henry Whitmarsh Pearse, perceived three sail standing towards her from the land. Being on contrary tacks, the two parties closed fast; and, when about four miles apart, the Halcyon discovered the strangers to be an armed ship, brig, and '''xebec'''.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=Thomas Pynchon|authorlink=Thomas Pynchon|chapter=Epilogue: 1919|title=[[w:V.|V.: A Novel]]|location=New York, N.Y.|publisher={{w|J. B. Lippincott &amp; Co.}}|year=1963|oclc=602193192|location2=New York, N.Y.|publisher2={{w|Bantam Books}}|month2=March|year2=1964|page2=19|pageurl2=https://archive.org/stream/vnovel00pync#page/18/mode/1up/|oclc2=924727755|passage=Winter. The green '''xebec''' whose figurehead was [[Astarte]], goddess of sexual love, tacked slowly into the Grand Harbour.}}
#* {{quote-book|en|author=Daniel Panzac|author2=John E. Hawkes|author3=Victoria Hobson, transl.|chapter=The Commercial Fleets of the Maghreb|editors={{w|Suraiya Faroqhi}} and {{w|Halil İnalcık}}|title=Barbary Corsairs: The End of a Legend 1800–1820|series=The Ottoman Empire and Its Heritage: Politics, Society and Economy|seriesvolume=29|location=Leiden|publisher=[[w:Brill Publishers|Koninklijke Brill]]|year=2005|pages=193–194|pageurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=_dyeFP5Hyc4C&amp;pg=PA193|isbn=978-90-04-12594-0|issn=1380-6076|passage=The choice of ship of the Maghrebi sailors was influenced above all by local traditions, by their different objectives, and by the availability of the vessels. It is apparent that the '''xebeck''', with its sleek lines, its reputation for speed—admittedly at the expense of its carrying capacity—was the preferred choice of the North Africans. It is true that the '''xebeck''' served in privateering and at least a percentage of the ships assigned to shipping merchandise were converted corsairs, with somewhat reduced gunpowder and much smaller crews.}}
====Alternative forms====
* {{alter|en|xebeck|chebeque|shebeck||archaic}}
* {{alter|en|zebec|zebeck}}
====Translations====
{{trans-top|transport ship}}
* Bulgarian: {{t+|bg|шебек}}
* Catalan: {{t+|ca|xabec|m}}
* Czech: {{t|cs|šebeka}}
* Dutch: {{t|nl|xebec}}
* French: {{t+|fr|chebec|m}}, {{t+|fr|chebek|m}}
* German: {{t|de|Chebeke|f}}, {{t+|de|Schebecke|f}}
* Greek: {{t|el|σεμπέκο}}
* Hungarian: {{t|hu|chebek}}
* Italian: {{t|it|sciabecco|m}}
* Japanese: {{t|ja|ジーベック}}
* Korean: {{t|ko|지벡}}
{{trans-mid}}
* Norwegian:
*: Bokmål: {{t|no|sjebek}}
*: Nynorsk: {{t|nn|sjebek}}
* Occitan: {{t|oc|chebèc|m}}
* Polish: {{t|pl|szebeka}}
* Portuguese: {{t+|pt|xaveco|m}}
* Russian: {{t+|ru|шебе́ка}}
* Serbo-Croatian: {{t+|sh|šebek|m}}, {{t+|sh|šambek|m}}
* Spanish: {{t+|es|jabeque|m}}
* Swedish: {{t|sv|chebeck|c}}, {{t|sv|schebeck|c}}
* Ukrainian: {{t|uk|шебе́ка}}
{{trans-bottom}}
===Further reading===
* {{pedia}}
[[Category:en:Watercraft]]</text>
<sha1>l92nxkfl2gaxhr60z7wt49l5y1mu3kc</sha1>
</revision>
</page>
